<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breife relation, of some of the most remarkable pasages of the Anabaptists in high and low Germany in the year, 1521. &amp;c. Gathered out of the writings of Sleyden, Antonius, Servanus, Lambertus, John Gastio, and others who write of their practises. And Bullinger, Luther, Melancthon, Calvin, Vrsinus, and others who write against their heresies. By George Pressick, of Dublin in Ireland.</title>
            <author>Pressick, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1047_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867089</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867089</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119379</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119379)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1047[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breife relation, of some of the most remarkable pasages of the Anabaptists in high and low Germany in the year, 1521. &amp;c. Gathered out of the writings of Sleyden, Antonius, Servanus, Lambertus, John Gastio, and others who write of their practises. And Bullinger, Luther, Melancthon, Calvin, Vrsinus, and others who write against their heresies. By George Pressick, of Dublin in Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Pressick, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Ratcliff,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "nouemb. 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119379:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A breife RELATION, of ſome of the moſt Remarkable Paſages of the ANABAPTISTS in High and low <hi>Germany</hi> in the year, 1521. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gathered out of the writings of <hi>Sleyden, Antonius, Servanus, Lambertus, John Gaſtio,</hi> and others who write of their Practiſes.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Bullinger, Luther, Melancthon, Calvin, Vrſinus,</hi> and others who write againſt their hereſies.</p>
            <q>
               <p>When the righteous are in authority, the people rejoyce: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourne.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 29.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For through covetouſneſſe ſhall they with fained words make merchandize of you, whoſe Judgement now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation ſlumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For ſuch are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt. And no marvell, for Satan himſelf is tranſformed into an Angell of light. Therefore it is no great thing if his ministers alſo be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as the miniſters of righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By GEORGE PRESSICK, of <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119379:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119379:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, <hi>Roger</hi> Lord <hi>Broghill,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> and Sir <hi>Theophilus Jones,</hi> Grace and peace be multiplied</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Righ Honour.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have four yeares ſince put forth a booke in anſwer to <hi>Mr. Thomas Patients</hi> book, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the doctrine of baptiſme, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction of Covenants, and <hi>I</hi> did expect, that, Mr. <hi>Patient</hi> would have replyed to mine, and therfore I did by reading provide my ſelf in part for a reioynder, but ſeing he hath not replyed, I have made bold to preſent to your <hi>Honours,</hi> ſomething of what I had gathered together, and by what I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> amongſt us: <hi>I</hi> have drawen up, I think the breifeſt relation that hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, of the moſt remarkable paſſages both of Doctrine and practice in <hi>Germany 139</hi> yeares ago, and ſo forward. In which, the Judicious Reader may obſerve, how near theſe Sectaries in theſe Nations have advanced both in Doctrine, and practiſe to theſe in that in <hi>Germany.</hi> And conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how God hath raiſed up your ſpirits, and how Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall your Honours have been, in the hand of God to
<pb facs="tcp:119379:3"/>ſuppreſse their inſolent, tyrannicall uſurped Authority, which they exerciſed over Gods people in this nation, to inſlave us to their inſatiable luſts, and alſo how God hath proſpered your Honors indeavours therein, beyond what we could in natural reaſon expect, in ſo ſhort a time. Which plainly demonſtrates the work to be of God, and yet we may and ought, and that upon well grounded reaſon own your Honours, as Gods inſtruments, to be the three chief worthyes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in this bleſſed work, and though there are many other gallant ſpirits in this land, that have acted their ſeverall parts, and are moſt honourable, yet none have attained to the Honor of the firſt three. I therefore humbly beg leave to dedicate my ſervice to your Honours, as your dues and my duty. Firſt for that your earneſt care and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for the defence of the proteſtant religion, and the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liberties of the people have manifeſtly appeared to all men. Secondly, that I may hereby acknowledge my humble thankfullneſſe Firſt to God the author of all good, Secondly to your Honors in hope of being a ſharer in this mercy of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as I have had a ſad ſhare in ſuffering, under their tyranny and wickedneſs, I humbly beg pardon for my preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I beſeech the God of heaven, to keep your hearts humble, and to deliver you from every evill way, untill he bring you to his Glory, which is the prayer of him, who is.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>February. <hi>1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours humble ſervant</hi> Gorge Preſſick, <hi>of</hi> Dublin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119379:3"/>
            <head>A breife Relation of ſome Remarkable Paſſages, of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> in High and low <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Gathered out of the writings of</hi> Sleyden, Antonius, Servanus, Lambertus, John Gaſtio, <hi>and others, who write of their practiſes. And</hi> Bullinger, Luther, Malancthon, Calvin, Urſinus <hi>and other who write Books againſt their Hereſies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rithenaeus Abbas, Aſpergenſis</hi> ſetts forth, in his Cronicle of the year, 1503. The diſpoſition of the commons in high, and low <hi>Germany.</hi> That there aroſe agreat ſedition of Peaſants about <hi>Bruxels,</hi> which he calls <hi>Liga Solutaria,</hi> which were ſworne to theſe Articles <hi>(viz)</hi> to ſhake off the yoak of all higher powers, and get liberty by force of Armes, to pull down all Magiſtrates, and kill all that ſhould ſtand againſt them, (I pray God bleſſe <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> from ſuch plotts) and they engaged to ſeize on the Citty of <hi>Bruxells,</hi> and invade the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden,</hi> and to ſeiſe on all the revenues of Monaſteries, Churches and Clergy men, to ſtay no where above twenty four hours, but to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtill, till they had brought many Countreyes in to their ſociety, to pay no more tithes, nor Lords rents, nor tribute, and who oever was received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that league, was to ſay five times a day on his knees one <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and one <hi>Ave Mary</hi> for the good ſucceſs of their Enterprize, and their word of Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance was the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt. But they were timely prevented, and the authors put to death, by <hi>Maximillian</hi> their Prince.</p>
            <p>But by this, we may ſee from whence <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Ranters,</hi> and <hi>Levelers;</hi> all had their originall, namely from the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> by their word of Cognizance and their <hi>Ave Maries</hi> and their <hi>Pater noſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you compare theſe with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and other their doings ſome few yeares fter, and now in this Age, in theſe Countryes, only the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> added ſomething more to their licentious rebellion, as their rebaptizing and poligamy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but both were varmiſhed with a Colour of religion: For about the year 1521. there aroſe a new ſect in <hi>Saxonr</hi> much like our <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> now, who boaſted, that they talked with God, and God with them, and had revelations, and that God Commanded them to kill all the wicked, and to make a new world, wherein the godly ſhall raigne alone <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Nicholas Stoke</hi> was the firſt that broached this opinion, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpake to him by an Angell, and revealed his will to him in dreams,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119379:4"/>promiſing him the place of the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> and the Empire of the world, he taught that the Saints muſt raigne in the world, and that he ſhould be their leader to kill all the Kings and Princes, and to purge the Church, he took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, to have the gift of deſcerning ſpirits, to know the elect, from repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates; he made holineſſe to conſiſt in ſpeaking little, and living homely and ſordidly, as our <hi>Quakers</hi> do.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Nicholas Stokes</hi> ſchoole was <hi>Thomas Muntzer</hi> bred, who amplified his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters doctrine, he began to teach at <hi>Alſtetum</hi> a place belonging to the Elector of <hi>Saxony.</hi> He tanght that his Conſorts muſt have a new baptiſme, And that Chriſtians muſt be of Auſtere Countenance, and ſpeak, little and weare long beards, and this he called the mortification of the fleſh, and that they ought to retyre into deſarts and private places he: aſcribed much to dreames.</p>
            <p>In that City he began to make a confederacy, adminiſtring an Oath, and taking the names of all them that promiſed to aſſiſt him in his deſigne of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all the ungodly and all Princes, and Magiſtrates, and erecting new ones in their places, profeſſing openly that he had commiſſion from God, to puniſh wicked Governours, and to change there civil policie, as <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have done with us, and for this cauſe being expelled out of <hi>Saxony,</hi> he wandered up and down <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Helvetia,</hi> ſowing the ſeeds of ſedition: at length he came to <hi>Mulhus,</hi> where many of his diſciples reſorted to him: where he prevailed in a ſhort time, to put down the Magiſtrates, and aſſumed to himſelf to judge all cauſes, both civil, and Eccleſiaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciall, affirming that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Teſtament, all cauſes muſt be judged by the word of God, and whatſoever he determined was received as an Oracle, eſpecially when he preached that all goods muſt be common, and all men free and of equall digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, an acceptable doctrine, where the Nobillity and Gentry oppreſſed the poor people, he gave alſo the Monaſteries for publike plunder; and thoſe that had Eſtates, if he could not perſwade them to give it by arguments, he took it from them by violence. No wonder then; if this new doctrine wonnemany of the meaner ſort to be of his opinion, who preſently left working, and what they wanted, they tooke from them that had it.</p>
            <p>About that time in <hi>Daringen, Fueva</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> forty thouſand Boars &amp; Trades men-roſe up in Armes, killed &amp; ranſacked a great part of the Nobility, pilledged and burned many forts and Caſtles, and overthrew all like a ſudden inundation: for the banks of authority being, beaten down no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſtop their ſuries, till they loſt themſelves in their own Confuſion by running venturers in that holy war.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Muntzer</hi>'s cheife aſſociate was on <hi>Henery Phiſer,</hi> one that gave much heed to dreames, and night viſions, and amongſt other viſions, he ſaid he had ſeen a great company of rats in a ſtable, and that he had driven them all away, which he interpretea as a command from God to take Arme and diſpoſſeſs all the the Nobility and Gentry. Whereupon he ruſhed into the Country, and pilledged Caſtles and Churches, deſtroyed many of the Nobles and brings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119379:4"/>ſome of them bound, and returnes with a great booty, which ſucceſſe raiſed the minds of the Boares, and cauſed another defection in the county of <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field:</hi> ſo <hi>Muntzer</hi> hoping that the rebellion was univerſall, taketh his journey from <hi>Mulhus,</hi> and is preſently ſupplyed with a Company of <hi>Franchuſians,</hi> but before he could do much more, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſtopped his courſe, for having raiſed in haſt ſome companyes of horſe, he falls upon him, and killed two hundred of his men; at which the rude Boares were ſo terrified, that they all fled to <hi>Franckhus,</hi> this skirmedge broke the edge of their fury, and gave time to <hi>John Electour</hi> of <hi>Saxony,</hi> &amp; his vncle <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Phillip Land-Grave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and <hi>Henery Duke</hi> of <hi>Brunſwik</hi> and <hi>Count Mansfield,</hi> to raiſe, Fifteen hundred horſe, and ſome Companies of foote. The Boares were pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched upon a hill by <hi>Frankhus,</hi> but very ill armed, and worſe diſciplined, the Princes ſent to offer them pardon, if they would yeild up the authours of the ſedition, but <hi>Muntzer</hi> underſtood not that Goſpell; and told the Boares that proffer came from the Princes fearfullneſſe, and that he was ſent of God to command, and lead them in that action, and their duty was to obey as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did, when he was commanded to offer his ſon, and that they ſhould ceartinly overcome theſe and all other enemyes. It being promiſed, that the righteous ſhould waſh his foote, in the bloud of the wicked From hence we may ſee how Satan transforming himſelf into an Angell of light, enters into and deludes poor people, untill he brings them to ruin; <hi>Muntzer</hi> further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to be valiant in the Lord, and to kill every mothers ſon, for an acceptable ſacrifice to the Lord. By this you may gueſſe, if <hi>Anabaptists, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Ranters</hi> ſhould get the upper hand, what they would do: <hi>Muntzer</hi> further aſſured them, that God himſelf had promiſed him victory, and indowed him with ſuch ſtrength, that he was able to turnt the bullet back with his coate, and perceiving a rainbow in the sky, he turned toward his Colours, where a rainbow was painted, look up ſaid he to heaven, here is a Joyfull ſign of Gods favour, the rainbow, the very Emblem of our Colours, and beſure that God promiſeth us to be our ſtandard bearer to fight for us himſelf.</p>
            <p>This new doctrine made a ſtrong impreſſion in ſome, but the Princes draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neare with a warlike march, made a ſtronger impreſſion of fear in that rude multitude than <hi>Muntzers</hi> revelations and ſignes, the Princes began to play with their Ordinance, one cannot well ſay to break their rankes, for they kept neither rank nor ſile, nor ſcarſe their underſtanding: for, for a time they neither advanced not fled, not put themſelves in a poſtuer of defence, only they had made ſome entrenchments, and they began to ſing, Come holy Ghoſt, expecting that God would fight for them, as their Generall <hi>Munt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> had promiſed them, and that he would turne back the bullets with his coate, but then all proved to be Satans deluſions, for the Princes advanced and came to handy blowes, away fled all the Boares, ſome one way, ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other five thouſand were flayne, <hi>Frankhus</hi> taken the ſame day, and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119379:5"/>taken and executed, <hi>Muntzer</hi> was found on a bed in <hi>Frankhus,</hi> ſayning him to be long ſick of an Ague, but the truth is, he was brain-ſick of gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die-mindedneſs, but letters being found about him, he was known to be <hi>Muntzer,</hi> which yet this lying Prohpet denyed long: he was executed by the common hangman, and his head ſet one a high pole, in the feild near <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hus,</hi> in the yeare 1525. ſhortly after <hi>Phiſer</hi> and other rebells were taken and executed at <hi>Mulhus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The rout then of theſe cracked brained ſeditious ſciſmaticks ſeemed to be rooted out, but the ſeeds remained; for in the year. 1527. aroſe another of great learning, his name was <hi>Micher Hopman</hi> with ſeverall others, they deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the incarnation of Chriſt in the virgins womb, Condemned the baptiſme of children, and rebaptized themſelves, and all that embraced that ſect, They would not allow Chriſtians to recover their own by law, nor to take an oath, nor to bear the office of a Magiſtrate, for they pulled down Magiſtrates where they had ſtrength, and gave the power of the ſword to their Miniſters, and Prophets, who was to decide all differences, they undertook to kill all Princes, &amp; cut off the ungodly with another ſword, than that of the ſpirit, they taught that in their Churches all were holy, and that none could be ſaved that would not make his goods common, and that it was lawfull to have many wives, and that all learning is prophane, and that mean men are the fitteſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Scripture, and that there muſt be no ordinary Calling in the Church, but every man muſt ſpeak as he is inſpired, and this is it which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Agents, that are amongſt them, who are their ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders, have been endeavouring in theſe three nations, theſe eight or nine years by paſt: They taught that Chriſt muſt raign over all the world, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Kings and Princes muſt de ſlayne, and what they taught they went really about to practiſe untill <hi>Hopman</hi> for his ſedition was impriſoned at <hi>Straſburg</hi> and his confederates repreſſed by the maigiſtrates, that crew diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves in <hi>Weſtphallia, Friſe, Holland</hi> &amp; moſt parts of the low countreys, where they got many to joyne with them, and when they were admoniſhed, and by arguments Confuted, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwer was that the Spirit taught them other wayes, and would ſay, the ſpirit bloweth where it liſteth as our <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Annabaptiſts</hi> ſay now, judging none to have the Spirit but themſelves, but their rage could not be kept in long, for ſometimes they would ruſh out of Cities and places where they were in great companies, and ranſack Convents, and great mens houſes; pretending for their warrant, the Example of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that took the ſpoile of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> yet in theſe incurſions, they made conſcience of entring into the temples of ſuch as were not rebaptized, as <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> but made no Conſcience to lye with their wives, as being left a prey for the godly.</p>
            <p>It is a Greife to tell how that in the City of <hi>Munſter,</hi> truth made way for errours, for one <hi>Bernard Rottman</hi> came to St. <hi>Maryes</hi> Church hard by <hi>Munſter,</hi> and for a time preached good Doctrine, as I fear many others do amongſt us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119379:5"/>for a time to get into favour. The people would have brought him into the Citty, but the Papiſts gave him a ſumme of money to depart, and he loving the wages of unrigteouſneſſe did depart for ſome time, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again, at which time ſome of the beſt ſort, brought him into the Citty, but the Papiſts kept the Church-dores ſhut, they made him a pulpit in the Church yard. <hi>Rotman,</hi> ſeeing the progreſſe of reformation, ſends to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purge,</hi> and deſires ſome Miniſters might be ſent to carry on the work of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, which was done ſo, that they challenged the Popiſh Clergy, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and preſented thirty Articles againſt them, and did ſo prevaile, that the Senat allowed the reformed party, ſix Churches in the City.</p>
            <p>Hitherto all went well, if it could have ſtayed there, in the interim comes a peſtilent <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> a Taylor of <hi>Leyden, John Becold</hi> by name; but better known by the name of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> this man begins to confer with Miniſters and people, mantaining the baptiſme of Children to be unlawfull, ſeducing many and ſowering the whole lump with the leaven of his perverſe doctrin, this was the year 1533. He being aſſiſted by one <hi>John Matthias,</hi> a Baker of <hi>Harlem,</hi> and one <hi>Harman Strapeda,</hi> who had been brought up with <hi>Henery Rell,</hi> a little before executed at <hi>Vtrech</hi> for his villany. With ſeverall others, theſe had their meetings in the night, and got a great party to joyne with them, who they incenſed with moſt deſperate reſolutions, many of them being the very filth of men, invited thither by the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> from neighbouring Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, till then <hi>Rotman</hi> did well, but ſeeing ſuch multitudes of <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> increaſing daily, he hunting after popular applauſe, joynes himſelf to them by an open revolt, the Magiſtrates and people not yet infected with that new ſeditious Doctrine, finding ſo much diſtraction amongſt them, commanded all forrainers, and ſectaries, to depart out of the City, but they went out at one gate and came in at another, ſaying, they muſt not deſert Gods cauſe: The Senate to prevent ſedition, appointed a publique conference, where <hi>Rotman</hi> and his faction appeared, but was oppoſed by a worthy divine, one <hi>Herman Baſilius,</hi> that the Senate was ſatisfied, and concluded for the truth, and the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> teachers were ſentenced to be baniſhed, but they being reſolved not to go, lay lurking among the ſectaries, whom they had poyſoned with their doctrine, and ſtill increaſed as they did of late here in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Anabptiſts,</hi> faining himſelf to be ſeiſed with a propheticall ſpirit, ran through the Citie crying, repent and be baptized again, or elſe the wrath of God will fall upon you, this ſtirred up the people, for many ran with him crying the ſame words, that many of the ſimpler ſort were baptized, ſome for fear of the wrath of God, and many for fear of the wrath of men, for this crying and running through the ſtreets, ended in ranſaking the beſt houſes, and laying violent hands on the owners, for many that lay hid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore came forth and ruſhed into the market place, crying out that all that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be killed preſently as ungodly, and heathens: and they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119379:6"/>ſeized on the Town-houſe, &amp; the weapons there, and began to dominere as in a conquered place. The other partie gathered themſelves in a place called <hi>Overwater,</hi> and both ſides were fortifying the places for three dayes, till hoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages were given on both ſides, and agreed that every one ſhould enjoy the freedome of his religion, and all ſhould go home in peace; this tumult was toward the end of <hi>December.</hi> 1533.</p>
            <p>But this would not ſatisfy the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for we now ſee by wofull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will either have all, or elſe they will not be ſatisfied: for this compoſition gave but time to the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for in 1534. <hi>Rotman,</hi> and <hi>Bernard Knipperdoling, &amp;c.</hi> Sent letters to <hi>Ousburg, Weſel, Croſwel,</hi> and <hi>Waringdorp;</hi> that God had ſent a holy Prophet to <hi>Munſter</hi> who ſpake wonders and ſhewed the right way to ſalvation, and that if they would leave their houſes and come to <hi>Munſter</hi> in all haſt, they ſhould get ten times more than they left, and with worldly riches, get alſo ſpirituall wealth.</p>
            <p>Theſe faire promiſes, drew all the ſcum of the neigbouring townes, to <hi>Munſter,</hi> the poor and Idle people liking well of that religion, that made all men alike, and all goods common, and put down the Magiſtrates: that ſhould reſtraine their licentiouſneſs. But can any man imagine, that all theſe were believers before they were rebaptiſed, that was wonne with this kind of doctrine, ſo pleaſing to the fleſh, as to ſhare other mens goods, and to have as many wives as they pleaſed, yet in a ſhort time the City was full of ſtrangers, and vagrants that looked upon the place as a land of promiſe, and that they muſt expulſe Cananites, the richeſt of the town being frighted at their comming, thought it their ſafeſt courſe quietly to give them place, and without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyſe to with raw themſelves out of the Citty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> ſeeing themſelves ſtrong, ran to St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church and burnt it, with all the houſes about it, and pillaged other Churches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>populated Convents and Colledges, and burnt a great Library, and drove all the proteſtants out of City but ſome few that they miſtook for <hi>Anabapiſts,</hi> drying get you hence all yee wicked, elſe ye ſhall be ſlain, and with ſuch violence they thruſt them out, that ſome women with Child, miſcarried in the tumult, and now they being maſters of the City, began to order their new ſtate, they made two Conſulls, <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> and <hi>Kapinbrook:</hi> and two and twenty Senatore, or Aldermen that had the civil power, and the Prophets wereto rule matterrs of religion, under which name they governed Church and Common-wealth, for all matters were within the compaſſe of religion, and what ever a Prophet ſaid to be revealed to him paſſed for law, the muſt famous of theſe Prophets was <hi>John Matthias,</hi> a Baker of <hi>Harlem,</hi> who was in effect, a perpetuall Dictator in <hi>Munſter</hi> that made lawes and thanged them at his pleaſure, by him was the aforeſaid Order made, his chief adjunct was <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and the next was <hi>Bernard Kniperdoling,</hi> and by a revelation of <hi>John Matthias,</hi> an order was made upon pain of death that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119379:6"/>all the gold and ſilver, and moveable goods in the town, ſhould be brought to the common ſtock. For which they appointed a publick houſe, the order was obeyed more for fear than conſcience. For two maides propheteſſes, took upon them to find out the fraud: to that common ſtock were brought all the goods of thoſe that were driven out of the City, with that common ſtock they kept four great Ordinaries, where all fed in common, none being allowed to diet at home unleſſe he were ſick, plenty of proviſion they had, and they husbanded it very ill, feaſting every day, untill the Biſhop beſeidged them, and began to cut off their victualls, and then they ſtinted themſelves, but with too large allowance, for the Towne was ſo ſtrong by nature, beſides the fortification, that the Biſhop deſpaired to take it but by famine.</p>
            <p>The Prophets then turned their care to the ſpirituall government, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that none ſhould keep any bookes but Scripture, and all the books that could be found but Bibles were brought to a publique place and burned: from executing of books, they fell to execution of perſons. For <hi>Hubart Trutling,</hi> a bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck-ſmith ſeeing <hi>John Matthias</hi> paſs by, ſaid there goes a ſhitten Prophet, for this offence he was brought before the congregation, and condemned to death: <hi>John Matthias,</hi> would himſelf be the executioner, and firſt he wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with an halbart, and after ſhot him through with a piſtoll, and then pardons him ſaying, that God was appeaſed, and that he had a revelation, the man ſhould not die, which proved falſe, for the poor man died in a few daies after: we may from hence ſee the truth of that in the 12 of Proverbs, <hi>the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel,</hi> though they call themſelves Saints &amp; Prophets.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Matthias,</hi> to make amends for his falſe revelation, when the man vvas dead, runs in a mad mood through the Citty, bearing a pike, Crying that God the father had commanded him, to drive the enemies from the Citty, and ſo ruſhed alone into the enemies Camp to drive them away, and was their ſlaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Matthias</hi> being dead, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> comforted the people ſaying, that he knew long before by revelation, that <hi>John Matthias</hi> ſhould die that death, and that himſelf ſhould marry his wife, which he did ſhortly after, though he had one before, but ſhe was one of ſingular beauty, able to make a luſty young Prophet of about ſix and twenty yeares old, as he was, to preach up the Doctrin of poligamy, which he did ſhortly after, and had Fifteen wives, but he fell to other work before to make way for that, in the <hi>interim Knipperdoling,</hi> came forth with a revelation, that they that were in high places ſhould be brought down to the loweſt, and the loweſt raiſed up to the higheſt We have ſeen this by wofull experience acted amongſt our ſelves. But <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> met him with another revelation, that ſeeing it was the heavenly fathers pleaſure that thoſe that were, higheſt ſhould be brought loweſt, he was ſent of God to put down <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> from his place of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and to make him the hangman, and for that purpoſe he gave him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119379:7"/>from God a ſword to execute Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But there was need of more revelations for the alteration of government: <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> was led by a propheticall ſpirit upon the City walls, where he put off his cloths, and ran naked through the Citty, crying, the kingdome of <hi>Sion</hi> is come; the kingdome of <hi>Sion</hi> is come. By which we may take notice by the way, that our <hi>Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Ranters,</hi> are acted by the ſame deluding ſpirit that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> was acted by: then <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> returned home, and falls into a deep propheticall ſleep and dreames three dayes, and three nights together, and being awaked, he comes forth and ſpeakes not a word, but by ſigns calls for a table book, as <hi>Zachariah</hi> did, and there he writes down the names of twelve men coblers, and tinkers, all trades men, but on Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Citty, to theſe he aſſigned the government of the commonwealth, putting down the order ſet up by <hi>John Matthias,</hi> affirming that was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good will, which he had received by revelation: In that table-book alſo he writ, and charged the preachers to teach the people, or elſe he would have it ratified by the congregations; which was, that a man is not tyed to one wife, but that he may marry as many as he pleaſeth, &amp; when his Doctors would not approve of that monſtrous paradox, he cited them before his twelve Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, &amp; there he recoverd his tongue keeping a great clamour, and throwing down his clothes upon the ground and the new teſtament upon them, ſwearing by that holy book, that the doctrine which he had announced, was revealed unto him from heaven, and threatned, that if they conſented not, God would withdraw his mercy from them, and to teſtifie his evidence of ſpirit and Power, he commanded the firſt oppoſer of that new Goſpell, to be beheaded, which was preſently done, and for three dayes together they preached for confirmation of that opinion, but the beſt confirmation was his own practice; for preſently he married three wives, one of which was the relict of the grand prophet <hi>John Matthias,</hi> and married again and again untill he had Fifteen wives; many followed his example, and it became a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great praiſe to have many wives.</p>
            <p>This ſeemes to have been the firſt motive, to move him to broach that doctrine. A ſouldeir of the Biſhops having changed partyes, was harboured in the houſe where <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> lay, and he obſerved in the night, that this holy Prophet left his own bed, and went to the ſervant womans bed. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> perceiving he was diſcovered, calls the ſouldier aſide, and gives him gold to keep his Counſell, but after miſtruſting the ſouldiers toung, he thought it ſafer to countenance the fact by a publique doctrine, of the lawfullneſs to have many wives: this doctrine then was readily imbraced, by thoſe whoſe Age and temper was ableſt to conſult with fleſh and bloud, none refrayning himſelf from having many wives for want or Coveteouſneſs, for their wives were kept upon the common ſtock, and after receiving that law, the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ran to the handſomeſt women in the City: ſtriving who ſhould be the firſt ſerved, and lay with them without any contract, ſo that within a few
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119379:7"/>dayes, there was ſcarce a woman of fourteen yeares of age but ſhe was violated.</p>
            <p>But thoſe of the City, that had ſome remnant of ſound minde, and groned under that tyrany: made a party and layd hold of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Kniperdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and the reſt of the prophets, but the frantick rabble, which was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt number took Armes, and reſcued their Prophets, and killed fifty of their adverſaries, moſt of them in cold bloud: and with ſeverall kinds of deviſed crueltyes: <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> encouraged the murtherers, crying, he that would do God ſervice ſhould give the firſt blow.</p>
            <p>Whileſt they were thus wiving, and thriving in <hi>Munſter,</hi> the Biſhop that beſieged them had fair play, if he had husbanded his time well, but hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he bore the charge of the ſeige himſelf, but was after aſſiſted with men and mony, by <hi>Harman</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Prince of <hi>Clevis,</hi> and others about which there was a meeting at <hi>Coblents, December</hi> the 13. 1534. But this delay gave time to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> to project new deſignes. He decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the ſpirit of prophecy was departed from him, and reſted upon <hi>John Tuſcocorer</hi> a <hi>Goldſmith</hi> of <hi>Warendorp</hi> whom he before hand had ſuborned to counterfeit an Enthuſiaſme and revelation from heaven, this new Prophet called the congregation together, and declared, that it was the will of the heavenly father, that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> ſhould be King of the univerſe, and that with mighty Armes he ſhould kill all other Kings, and Princes: and deſtroy all the ungodly, and ſave the people that love righteouſneſs. Whereupon <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> fell on his knees and lifting up his hands ſaid, men and brethren, ſo much. I knew long ago, but would not reveale it until now, God hath made choiſe of another to bear witneſſe of that truth, Then ſaid <hi>Tuſcocorer,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, as I made <hi>Saul</hi> King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and after him <hi>David</hi> taken from the ſheepfold. I have ſet <hi>John Becold</hi> to be King in <hi>Sion,</hi> give eare, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou ſhalt abrogate thy magiſtrates and put down thy preachers, and in ſtead of them, eſtabliſh twelve ſimple men, without learning Arts and tongues, and they ſhall read my word, unto my people, and without any help, but my ſpirit expound it, and hath not this been the practice of Taylors and Coblers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> amongſt us: and into them will I pour the ſpirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding, then giving a ſword to <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>John Becold.</hi> To thee, Father <hi>Beccold</hi> ſaith he, the Father giveth this ſword, and calleth thee not onely to be King in <hi>Sion,</hi> but over all the world, and to extend thine Empire unto the ends of the earth, this oracle was follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great ſhouting, and acclamations of the people, crying, God ſave the King, and as it was then with theſe, ſo it is now amongſt us, if they could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile to bring their Enterprizes to paſs, our <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> would neither have King Magiſtrats, nor miniſters but of themſelves, one Grande ſaid, he hoped that before <hi>Mayday,</hi> there ſhould not be a man in the land ſhould he imployed in any places of truſt but ſuch as walked in their way, meaning as <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> they would have kings but of their own fraternity, inſtead of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119379:8"/>having one King, but of their owne fraternity, for inſtead of having one King, they would have five hundred Kings: for every man that had any command would raigne as a King in his precincts, ſome by woefull experience have found it ſo: they would have Parliaments too, but of themſelves, and their own chooſing, they would take away the priviledges of the people from chooſing, and deſtroy all the fundamentall lawes of the Land, they would have miniſters too, but they ſhould be ſuch as were without learning, ſuch as <hi>John Tuſcocorer</hi> propheſied, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> ſhould have in ſtead of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſters: their threatning, ſlighting, and deſpiſing Miniſters, and endeavouring to make fewer Pariſhes and fewer Miniſters makes the truth of this appeare to all mens ſight, that is not willfully blinde.</p>
            <p>This new King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> created four Councelours of State, the cheif whereof, was one <hi>Gerard</hi> a booke-binder, and one <hi>Talbek</hi> he made Lord ſteward of his houſhold, and one <hi>Kipinbrok</hi> Treaſurer of his plate and Jewells, and <hi>Kinperdoling</hi> Governour of the Citty, and appointed twelve Archers for his guard.</p>
            <p>This Taylor King preſently made uſe of his skill to make himſelfe fine in clothes, he tranſlated the copes, and carpets of Churches and Convents they had robbed, into doublets and breeches and cloaks, which ſet out his Majeſty all in gold and ſilver; his horſe wore a ſutable livery, with gold and ſilver ſaddles, &amp; foot cloths: thus he appeared abroad, having his cheife Officers riding before him in ſtate, next to him rid two young men richly attired, one carrying a naked ſword, with a golden hilt ſet with precious ſtones, the other carryed a Bible, and tripple Crown of gold glittering with diamonds, himſelf wore a great chain of Gold about his neck, like a coller of ſome noble Order, with a golden globe, having a golden ſword, through it, hanging at the chaine with this Motto. <hi>John</hi> King of new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the king of Righteouſneſſe of, this whole world, after him followed Fifty Pencioners with party coloured garments of aſh colour and Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe green, and white caps, and golden rings on every fingar, making the Aſh coulour an emblem of mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the graſſe green of regeneration, the white caps of innocence, the golden rings of charity, but amongſt theſe propheticall riddles, he ordered his court, with ſo much ſtate as, if he had been a King borne, truly but that ſo many godly orthodox divines, have written of theſe things that lived in that Age, and in thoſe countries, we could ſcarce have believed that men ſhould be given up to ſuch deluſions and that we ſee others amongſt us partly treading the ſame ſteps.</p>
            <p>In that royall array he ſhewed himſelf three times a week, and went up to a high throne ſet up with great magnificence, where he judged all controverſies, moſt of which were about divorce, for by his new goſpell any man that were weary of his wife, might put her away and take another, this was the king of <hi>Sions</hi> Government. Then this jolly Taylor King having ſtitched up a kingdom
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119379:8"/>in haſt, turnes his care to go through ſtitch with it, to have ſupply to remove the ſeige, and becauſe it ſhould be done in a propheticall way, <hi>Tuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>corer</hi> his cheife Agent, came to him it ſeemes by his appointment, as he ſate on his throne and told him, King <hi>John,</hi> The Goſpell muſt be renewed by thee, thus ſaith the Lord God, go ſay to the King of <hi>Sion,</hi> that he prepare my holy ſupper in the great Church yard, and chooſe teachers to ſend into the four quarters of the world, to teach the wayes of righteouſneſs, &amp; according to this <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> have gone all <hi>Ireland</hi> over, a publique Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was celebrated of above four thouſand men, but at that time the King accuſed a man of treaſon, and cut off his head with his own hand and with that bloudy hand, he tooke upon him to adminiſter the Sacrament, being aſſiſted by the <hi>Queen,</hi> ſometime wife to the lying Prophet, <hi>John Matthias,</hi> who then did the office of a miniſter: after ſupper the King asked them if they were all willingly diſpoſed to do the will of God, and to ſuffer &amp; dy for the faith, they anſwered they were all of that minde then <hi>Tuſcocorer</hi> their Prophet read a note the names of thoſe he ſaid God had choſen for that legation, of whom himſelf was cheife, they were twenty ſix, ſeaven were ſent to <hi>Oſneburg,</hi> ſix to <hi>Cockswold,</hi> five to <hi>Warendorp</hi> and eight to <hi>Suzat;</hi> theſe new Apoſtles went crying in the ſtreets of theſe Cities that the people ſhould repent and joyne with them, or elſe they ſhould ſhortly periſh, with that noyſe they raiſed tumules, and were apprehended and brought before the Magiſtrates, to whom they ſayed they were ſent of the Father to offer them peace, when it was but <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> that ſent them, which peace they ſaid, if they refuſed, Gods wrath would follow for their hardneſſe of heart and ungratefullneſs, this was juſt like our <hi>Quakers</hi> doctrin now, and they affirmed that the time was come, fore propheſied of that the whole world ſhould follow righteouſneſs, which God would work by their King, and then he ſhould deliver up the kingdom to his Father, and being queſtioned before the Magiſtrates, about their faith, they ſaid that none in the world had the true doctrine but they, which they would ſeale with their bloud, and that ſince the Apoſtles time till then the word of God had not been purely preached, that there was four great Prophets in the world, two good which was <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Delft,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and two bad, the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> Being asked by what Scripture they could juſtifie their depoſing ſo many good men from their houſes, and goods, and make ſo bold with their wives; they anſwered that the meek ſhould inherit the earth, and that in the ſame manner, God gave the <hi>Egyptians</hi> goods to the <hi>Jsraelites,</hi> &amp; a mongſt goods they reckoned wives, and that they might lawfully have as many as they pleaſed, ſo that when one was with child they might take another in her ſtead, and they put away barren women and paſt childe bearing, as uſeleſs, and that they knew by revelation, that their King wuld ſhortly be King of the whole earth &amp; denyed all other Magiſtrates but their own King, for which they were put to death, and here was the end of their Apoſtleſhip, that ſhould have preached a goſpell of rebellion, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119379:9"/>licentiouſneſſe over all the world, this was in <hi>December.</hi> 1534.</p>
            <p>To draw towards the laſt Act, of that wild King among the Prophets that were taken, on <hi>Henery Hilverſum</hi> was ſaved by the Biſhop in ſallying out of the Citty, who let him go, and he returned into <hi>Munſter.</hi> 1535. and ſaid God had delivered him out of priſon by an Angel, and told the King that God had given him three rich Cities, that ſhould imbrace his party, namely, <hi>Amſterdam, Deventer,</hi> and <hi>Weſſel;</hi> for which newes the King made him one of his Court, and diſpatched away one <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Kemp</hi> to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to bring it to his obedience, ſoon after the King hearing that many of his ſect were in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Frize</hi> in great troops, as ſheep without a ſhepherd, he ſent one <hi>John Giles,</hi> with a great ſumme of money, that he like another <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould be their leader through the wilderneſſe to bring them to <hi>Canaan,</hi> that was to <hi>Munſter,</hi> but when much time was paſt, and he heard nothing of theſe <hi>Jsrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> nor their <hi>Moſes,</hi> he ſent the Prophet <hi>Hilverſum</hi> and one <hi>John Nortell,</hi> to <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Frize</hi> to haſten them, or to raiſe new troops, and for that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition he loaded <hi>Hilverſum</hi> with as much gold as he could well beare. It ſeemes he propheſied for gold, and he had now gotten it, therefore he went no further than the Biſhops camp, &amp; there ſtayed, &amp; writ a letter to the people in <hi>Munſter,</hi> that his former propheſies were impoſtures, exhorting them to open their eyes and ſee how they were deluded by acompany of raſcalls, and what beaſtly lives they led, and how near they were to deſtruction. <hi>John Nortell</hi> went as farre as <hi>Deventer</hi> and ſoone after returned without effect, this letter moved ſome of the people, for their community of goods was violated, they had their bread by weight, but their King ſtill feaſted. Which one of his wives diſliking ſaid, ſhe thought it not pleaſing to God, in ſuch a publique miſery, while ſome pined with hunger, others ſhould ſurfet with plenty, the King being told it, brought her to the market place with his other wives, made her kneel down and cut off her head, and made his other wives to ſing and give praiſe to their heavenly Father: at the ſame time two young men were taken running away and brought to the King, who killed them both with his owne hands, and to appeaſe the people, he told them that he would not have thought that they being borne again by a new baptiſme, would ſhew themſelves ſo impatient in their ſuffering for Gods cauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ſhould with <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffer hunger, cold and nakedneſſe to attaine ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Easter</hi> came, at which time their King had promiſed them deliverance, but his diſciples he had ſent to <hi>Hollond</hi> and <hi>Friſe,</hi> not the rabbel route he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected came not, which put the Prophet King to a plunge, he ſhut up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſix dayes, and fained himſelf ſick, and then came forth to the people, and ſaid, God had in his ſickneſſe ſet him upon a blind aſſe, and layed upon him the ſinnes of the whole multitude, whereby they were freed from their ſinne, and this was the deliverance God had promiſed them at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> this poor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119379:9"/>Lord of <hi>Miſrule,</hi> King <hi>John</hi> all his hopes being fruſtrate, could no longer pacifie the people, for famin was ſo feirce, that horſes, dogs &amp; cats were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, the graſſe and the very root; were picked out of the ground, in that extremity the King commanded the gates to be ſet open, and that ſo many as would ſhould go forth, ſo that in one day a thouſand of all ages and ſexes went out, and yielded themſelves to the Prince, who received them, ſed them, and let them go.</p>
            <p>A few dayes after, the King proclaimed that as many as wanted faith in Gods help ſhould avoyd the towne, but withall he ſaid thoſe that would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the faith ſhould be forſaken of God, many were ſo blindly zealous, his ſpeeches ſtayed them, yet many were ſo fed with ſtarved mice, broiled ſhoes &amp; lean propheſies, they took the ſafety proſered them. <hi>Antomius Corvinus</hi> a <hi>Luther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> divine writes, that he had ſeen books, when the town was taken, whoſe covers were eaten in the famine. Children half eaten were found, yet the King had ſix moneths proviſion left for his own family, the town was taken in <hi>Iune</hi> 1535. having indured a left of eighteen moneths. Upon the ſurprize, the Towns-men cryed for quarter and had it, but the King reſiſted to the laſt in St. <hi>Lamberts</hi> Church-yard, and was with much ado taken with <hi>Kniperdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and <hi>Krechling</hi> another Prophet, and <hi>Rotman</hi> would not yeild, but was ſlain in the Conflict.</p>
            <p>The King and no King, was ſent Priſoner to a caſtle four miles from <hi>Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter,</hi> he went thither a little faſter then he would, being tyed to the tayle of a galloping horſe, <hi>Kniperdol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> and <hi>Krechling</hi> were ſent priſoners to another place, ſoone after all three were brought to Telgate where the Biſhop asked <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> by what authority, he made himſelf King over his City, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> asked him again, who had given him authority over that City and people, he anſwered he came to it by election, and I ſayd <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> came in by the will and calling of God, two <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divines were ſent to conferre with <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Kniperdoling;</hi> the firſt did abujre many of his errors, and would hear reaſons. But <hi>Kniperdoling,</hi> was like a mad beaſt would neither hear nor anſwer reaſon, but ſtood only upon revelation &amp; a particular ſpirit as our <hi>Quakers</hi> do, they were condemened and executed as <hi>Traytors</hi> &amp; <hi>Rebels,</hi> &amp; <hi>Krechling</hi> ſuffred the like death. <hi>J.</hi> of <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> hearing the ſentence read, he confeſſed that indeed he had offended the Magiſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s but not offended God, thus died this imaginary K of juſtice by the hand of juſtice, and there was the end of his kingdome and propheſies, he was about twenty ſix years of age, a luſty young Prophet, of a fair proportion, of an awfull yet lovely preſence, of a preſent wit, eloquent, cloſe, politique, ambitious, which aſpired to no leſſe then the dominion of the world; he was a dangerous inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Satan, the good Lord deſtroy the plots of ſuch where ever they are.</p>
            <p>What other tumults were raiſed in <hi>Frezeland, Holland,</hi> and other places by the <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> crew, eſpecially in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and <hi>Leyden,</hi> may be ſeen at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the province &amp; beſotted the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119379:10"/>minds eſpecially of the vulgar ſort under the colour of ſimplicity, ſincerity, humility, charity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that many, otherwiſe good and zealous perſons, ſided with them, and were deluded by them, as too many do at this day.</p>
            <p>But theſe ſectaries brake into Fractions, and like new Incendiares proſecuted each other with inveterate minds, and writings, thundering againſt one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and delivering each other to Satan: to ſet forth their ſeverall opinions were almoſt impoſſible, but it is well known that then, and now at this day, they are divided into ſeverall Claſſes, and names derived either from their Ring-leaders, or from the courſe of life they follomed, or the place of their entertainment.</p>
            <p>In the front are placed the <hi>Muntzerians,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Muntzer,</hi> that grand incendiary their generall; others were called <hi>Hulites,</hi> from <hi>John Hull,</hi> who his after example called themſelves the Corporal <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God: he taught that all the <hi>Cananites</hi> were to be cut down with the ſword, and that the day of judgement was at hand, that the angel was ſounding the laſt trumpet: others were called the <hi>Hopmannians</hi> from <hi>Melcher Hopman,</hi> one furniſhed with popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar eloquence, he firſt grew famous at <hi>Argentum,</hi> and drew a great ſort of Diſciples after him, that they cryed him up for <hi>Elias:</hi> others were called <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetians</hi> from <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who for his execrable and not once to be named blaſphemies, againſt the ſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Trinity ſpread abroad &amp; maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great obſtinacy, and other wickedneſs, he was burnt at <hi>Geneva,</hi> breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out his ſoul in blaſphemies. The <hi>Davideans</hi> had their denomination from <hi>David, George a Batavian,</hi> an infamous Impoſter, both for blaſphemies and ſhamefull luſts, who came to that height of impiety, as to arrogate to himſelf to be Chriſt the Lord, to be the eternall ſon of the eternal Father, to apply to himſelf the propheſies concerning Chriſt our Saviour, which blaſphemies and other dotages he compiled into a book intituled wonders, but was bitterly inveighed againſt, even by other <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> whereupon he renounced his own name, and ſled, calling himſelf by the name of <hi>John</hi> a <hi>Bruck,</hi> he went to <hi>Baſill</hi> a famous Citty, where with the direfull ſting of an accuſing conſcience, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then any bodily infirmity he dyed: all theſe miſcreants with an outward forme of godlineſſe, drew multitudes of followers after them.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1535. It was diſcovered that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> had a plot to ſet <hi>Leyden</hi> on fire by night, and although timely notice was given, fire was ſet in ſeverall places of the town, houſes were ſearched, and the cheif of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours taken together in one houſe, fifteen men and five women, the men were beheaded, and the women drowned, and ſo baptized the third time.</p>
            <p>The neath moneth in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> one <hi>Theodoret</hi> a taylor, who beare himſelf for a Prophet, fell upon his face, and prayed with great vehemency, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as it were out of an extaſie I have ſeen God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119379:10"/>Heaven, then he ſaid he deſcended into Hell, and ſearched every corner. Its poſſible Mr. <hi>Gray</hi> might deſcend from that Tribe, he knowe's Hell ſo well, becauſe he declares He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to be paved with Kings crovvne, and Biſhops Sculls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thou, ſaith this Prophet to one of the company, art not good enough for Hell, then the poor condemned man fell on his knees craving pardon and the Prophet anounced him a full remiſſion of all his ſinnes, another night the Prophet and ſix men more and five women, vvho had left their husbands in bed met in a houſe, after ſome time ſpent in prayer and teaching, the Prophet ſtripped off all his cloaths, and his ſhirt, and threvv all into the fire, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them all to do the like, &amp; they did ſo, the women having not ſo much as a hairface, nor any thing to hide their ſhame: for the Prophets pleaſure was to burne all as a ſweet ſacrifice to God, then he commanded them to follow him, &amp; ſo running &amp; his diſciples after him through the ſtreets, they cryed horribly Woe, Woe, Woe, the divine vengearce, the divine vengeance, which put the whole town in an uprore, thinking they had been ſurprized by ſome ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: they were all taken but one woman that ſlopped aſide, and brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Magiſtrates, and they ſtood naked before Court, they refuſed garments offered to cover them, ſaying they muſt have no covering, for they were the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aked truth, they were kept in priſon till the great conſpiracy, about two months after, and then executed.</p>
            <p>In another Town at noon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, five <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ran naked through the ſtreetes with ſwords in their hands, crying, in the name of the Lord, that the bleſſing of God lay upon one part of the Towne, and his curſe on the other part, and ſoone after were followed, with others of the ſame faction in Armes, but the Magiſtrates raiſed in haſt ſome companies of Archers to oppoſe them, the Authors of the ſedition were taken &amp; the reſt quieted for a time. The ſame day ſuch another ſedition was raiſed at <hi>Harlem,</hi> in which ſix <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were ſlaine, and two at the <hi>Hague</hi> were executed ſhortly after, ſix of the moſt ſeditious were burnt at <hi>Harlem,</hi> and two women d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owned</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Gaſtio</hi> in his Book ſaith, it was their conſtant doctrine that women muſt be common, and three reaſons they gave for it worthy to be regiſtred, to perſwade honeſt women to proſtitute their bodies, if they would be ſaved: the firſt was that Chriſtians muſt renounce thoſe things they love beſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore women muſt renounce their beloved honeſty. The ſecond was, that for Chriſts ſake, we muſt undergo any kind of infamy, the third was that Publicans and harlots go to heaven before Phariſees, lying with other women than their wives they called ſpirituall marriages, with that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin they had ſeduced two ſiſters at St, <hi>Gall near Zurick</hi> as <hi>John Gaſtio</hi> writes in his third Book p. 21. ſoon after they were rebaptiſed, being in bed two ſpirituall huſbands came and lay with them, but with ſuch fervent ſpirit that they brake the bottom of the bed, the noiſe whereof wakened the people in the houſe, who coming up in haſt to know the matter, found two ſpirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119379:11"/>
            <p>They had another main reaſon for community of women, that as Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> are all one ſpirit, ſo they muſt be all one body: its very like the <hi>Ranters</hi> teach theſe: doctrins now the author ſaith that theſe two poor maids of St. <hi>Gall.</hi> before they were <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> had been much ſolicited, and could never be won untill they were <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and then were perſwaded to be whores for conſcience ſake: others under pretence of childiſh innocency, would ride naked upon ſticks, and hobby horſes like children in great companies, and women would run naked with them, and then in pure innocency they lay together, ſo in the end it proved to be childrens play indeed.</p>
            <p>In the ſame town one being in his propheticall mood, called his father, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, brothers &amp; ſiſters together, &amp; commanded his brother to kneel down, &amp; with one blow he cut off his head, and ſaid the will of God was done, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before the Burgomaſter, he ſaid I announce unto thee, the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it being the year 1541. a day which two yeares before they had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told ſhould be the day of Judgement: but the Burgomaſter announced him his day of judgement, and he was executed as he deſerved.</p>
            <p>It were almoſt an endleſs peice of work, to reckon up all their Doctrines and practiſes, but this I have gathered to give an hint of their wofull proceedings, where they got to any head, &amp; we may ſee the ſad ſymptomes hereof amongſt our ſelves, ſome have not ſpared to ſay, they hoped within a ſhort time, there ſhould not be a miniſter left in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and have they not rooted out the Parliaments and all the fundamentall lawes of theſe lands, and as <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> did, aſſumed a uſurped power to themſelves to make lawes, and aboliſhed lawes at their pleaſure, and exerciſed tyranny and oppreſſion over the poor people, and have they not aſſumed a regall power, if their wings be not clipt, to call a Parliament of their own, with no leſſe then one and twenty Kings, I mean officers of the Army, to have a negative vote in the Parliament, ſo that if God do not reſtraine them, and ſtir up his people to withſtand them, It is to be feared the conſequence that will follow may prove as bad, if not worſe, then their proceedings in <hi>Germany,</hi> yet they call themſelves Saints and holy people, and righteous perſons, and all others that differ from them in not being rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed they counted wicked and ungodly and heathens, not yet come out of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> whereas upon tryall there will little difference be found between them &amp;, thoſe you read of in <hi>Numbers</hi> 16.3. <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abyram,</hi> for juſt ſo they dealt with Magiſtrates and Miniſters. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> as theſe do with ours now, ſeeing ye take too much upon you, ye ſomes of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſeeing all the Congregation is holy every one of them, to theſe three <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rah, Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han</hi> and <hi>Abyram</hi> We may compare the three ringlerders of <hi>Anabaptists, Quakers</hi> and <hi>Ranters</hi> for as then <hi>Corah, &amp;c.</hi> gathered two hundred and fifty Princes famous in the Congregation, men of renown to take part with them in their rebellion. So theſe in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> have gathered, I may juſtly ſay two hundred and fifty Officers in the Army, famous in the Congregation, men of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119379:11"/>them to take too much upon them, ſeeing all their Congregations arch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in their own eſteme every one of them. And thefore like <hi>Thomas Munſter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> they would either remove or kill all Princes and Magiſtrates; and all the ungodly, and root out miniſtery, but what the end was of theſe wicked men for their rebellion, The Chapter ſhewes at large, and the two hundred and fifty that took their parts, and with their braſſe cenſers offered ſtrange fire as <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> did. <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>Fire came out from God and Conſumed them.</hi> I deſire theſe fearfull examples of Gods diſpleaſure may be a warning to others, for in due time God will ſhew who are holy, and who not holy, and as in <hi>Revela.</hi> 2.2. He will try them that ſay they are Apoſtles, &amp; are not but, are liars, &amp; thoſe that call themſelves <hi>Jews,</hi> as ſome of the <hi>Quakers</hi> do, and are not but of the Synagogue of Satan <hi>ver.</hi> the 9. and thoſe that call themſelves Prophets &amp; Propheteſſes and are not, but teach re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and ſeduce the people, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. He will alſo try thoſe that ſay they are Saints, and are not but live more like <hi>Heath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> and thoſe that ſay they are Chriſt and are not, as <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and <hi>James Millner</hi> of <hi>Beakley</hi> in <hi>Lancaſheer,</hi> who alſo ſaid that <hi>George Fox</hi> was <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, ſuch falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and propheſies as theſe we have heard too much of in theſe three Nations of late, ſo that it behoves all godly perſons both civil and military and Miniſters and people to endeavour by all lawfull meanes to defend the truth againſt ſuch ſeducers.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Certain reaſons againſt ſome Points of Popery, which they are deſired to anſwer if they can.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Of works of Supererogation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, we demand being the Pope doth brag that he hath in the treaſury of the Church, the ſuperabounding paines and travells of Saints, <hi>Munks, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> and others, which is called works of <hi>Supererogation,</hi> and which the Pope converteth into payment, for the paniſhments due unto others, diſtributing them by indulgence; We demand who hath put the ſuffering of the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into the Popes treaſury to be thus diſtributed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we demand when this diſtribution began.</p>
               <p>Thirdly how ſhall we be aſſured that God will receive that payment for us.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, We demand why God ſhould receive ſuch payment for us, ſeeing the death of Jeſus Chriſt is ſufficient payment.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, how do ye prove that Jeſus Chriſt doth give to any one that vertue to pay a debt which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ lines">
                     <desc>〈1… lines〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119379:12"/>
               <p>Sixthly, hath the Pope alſo in the Treaſury of the Church, the puniſhment and travells of <hi>Noah, Abraham, Jacob</hi> and others, and to whom doth he diſtribute them.</p>
               <p>Seaventhly, why did not the Sacrificers in the time of the law diſtribute them to the faithfull in their times?</p>
               <p>Eightly, why did not Jeſus Chriſt; nor the Apoſtles, nor their diſciples, in all the firſt Age of the Church diſtribute any indulgence unto the dead.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, why was it that they did not celebrate any <hi>Jubile,</hi> nor eſtabliſh any ſuch priviledges as the Pope doth, now, whereupon he that cauſeth certain Maſſes to be ſaid, draweth a ſoule whom he will chuſe out of Purgatory, nor give any bulls to deliver a foul out of <hi>purgatory,</hi> nor tye the remiſſion of ſinnes to a certain place, where the pardons are to be procured? Is it becauſe the Popes have better inventions than the Apoſtles and others had, or that God is grown more liberall than he was in former, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, how do you prove that there are any workes of <hi>Supererogation</hi> ſeeing God requires that we ſhould love and ſerve him with all the heart, and all the ſoule, and all the ſtrength, and all the mind; Now if God requires all, who is he that can do more than all, that he ſhould beſt of ſuperabounding workes more than God requires, when he requires all.</p>
               <p>For whatſoever any man can do, or performe that is lawfull to be done, it is included in this word, All, and it is either expreſſed or included in ſome command or precept in the word of God: and if it be not expreſſed nor included in the word of God, then God will ſay of it as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h required this at your hands,</hi> and God will eſteem of it, as he ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. <hi>He that killeth on oxe is as if he ſlew a man,</hi> and he that Sacrificeth a lamb, as if he cut off a dogs neck, and he that offereth an oblation, as if he offered ſwines bloud, and he that burneth incenſe, as, as if he bleſſed an Idoll, and the reaſon is given in the latter part of the verſe, they have choſen their own wayes, and their ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l delighteth in their abominations, for whatſoever you do that is not either expreſſed nor included in ſome command or precept, in which God requires all; it is your owne ways, and abominations, and not Gods wayes, and therefore God will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it. <hi>Ergo</hi> there is no works of <hi>Supererogation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Secondly of <hi>Merits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, how do you prove by Scripture, that any man can merit any good at the hands of God, ſeeing Chriſt himſelf tells us, that when we have done all that we can, we ſhould count our ſelves unprofitable ſervants, and have done no more than what is our duty to do, and therefore not meritorious as to Eternall life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the favour of God, ſaith Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> is of ſuch infinite dignity, that no creature is able to do a work to countervaile the favour of God, but Chriſt alone.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſaith he, for one good work we do, we do many evill works, the offence whereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faceth the merit of our beſt works, and makes them too light in the ballance of the law of God.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>God ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wes mercy unto thouſands of them that love him, and keep his Commandments.</hi> Exod. 20 6. Whence we reaſon thus, that where reward is given upon mercy, there it is not given upon merit, but reward is given upon mercy, even to them that love him and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments the refore not given upon merit.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Chriſt himſelf hath taught us to pray, give us our daily bread, it muſt needs therefore, ſaith Mr <hi>Perkias,</hi> be a Satanicall inſolency for any man to think that he can merit eternall life, who cannot merit bread; but ought daily to pray for it.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle, <hi>Titus.</hi> 5.3. ſaith, that it is not for any works of righteouſneſſe that we have done, but of mercy we are ſaved, and if of mercy, then it is not of merit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Thirdly of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, whereas Papiſts teach that Jeſus Chriſt is the interceſſor and meadiator for thoſe ſouls which they ſay are in Purgatory. We demand why they do not preſently go forth upon his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, but remaine ſome hundred or thouſand yeares, as appeares by five or ſix thouſand year pardons, which the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e grantetth, unleſſe you thinke that there is more efficacy in the Popes pardons then there is in Chriſts inerceſſion, anſwer it if you can.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we demand how it comes to paſſe that other religious men now a dayes in ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119379:12"/>
                  <hi>Carmelites</hi> have the priviledge granted them by the Pope, that they ſhall not be in Purgatory but till the Saturday after their death, and the <hi>Cordilians</hi> have this priviledge granted them to draw a ſoul out of Purgatory, by ſaying five <hi>Pater Nosters,</hi> and five <hi>Ave Maiyes,</hi> why have not the <hi>Jeſutes</hi> the like priviledge, and how prove you that the <hi>Carmelites</hi> and <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilians</hi> have ſuch priviledges.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we demand if the Pope have power to grant ſuch priviledges to others, and have power himſelf, as ſome hold by way of juriſdiction, or by way of ſuffrage, if he have ſuch power as he pretendeth, and your Church teacheth, then why doth he not take them all out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory? why doth he ſuffer his children to lye in a burning fire ſo many hundred yeares, if he be able to deliver them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>Fourthly of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> ſaith that in the firſt Inſtitution before Chriſts paſſion, the body of Chriſt was Sacramentally eaten as already ſacrificed, now how the body of Chriſt Crucified ſhould after a corporall manner be eaten, he being not as yet Crucified, is impoſſible to imagin.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we demand whether the Prieſt breake in the Maſſe the ſame thing that Jeſus Chriſt brak in the ſupper with his diſciples, for it is evident that our Lord brak bread, whence it follows that he brake nothing but bread, but the Preiſt breaketh after conſecration, by virtue of which conſecration, you ſay the elements are changed into the real body and bloud of Chriſt, and if ſo, then you actually Crucify Chriſt afreſh, breaking him in peices both with your hands and, teeth, putting him to open ſhame, and yet the Preiſt ſaith he ſacrificeth in breaking, which if it be true, prove it by Scripture, and who gave you this authority thus to ſacrifice Jeſus Chriſt, he being now in heaven.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we do not find in Scripture that the Apoſtles did adore that which Jeſus Chriſt gave them, as now the Papiſts do, neither do we find that Chriſt in his adminiſtring the ſupper, ſpake any thing of ſacrifice, nor made any elevation of the hoſt, as you now do, he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated it to all the aſſiſtants, ſpake in a language underſtood of all, why then is it at this day the Preiſt doth quite contrary.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if there be a reall Corporall preſence in the Sacrament, as Papiſts pretend, and that ſhortly after the Apoſtles had received it in their ſtomacks, Jeſus Chriſt did ſweat drops of bloud, and was apprehended and buffeted, Then we demand, if that body of Jeſus Chriſt, which was in the ſtomacks of the Apoſtles, if it did alſo ſweat drops of bloud, and was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and buffeted by the ſouldiers, for if it did ſweat drops of bloud, and was apprehended, under the ſpecies in the ſtomacks of the Apoſtles, it was paſſable, and alſo the ſouldiers that muſt buffet it, muſt be put under the ſame ſpecies, but if it did not ſweat nor was not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended nor buffeted under theſe kinds, then there as wat the ſame time a leſus Chriſt ſuffering, and a Jeſus Chriſt not ſuffering, and ſo by conſequence who was not our Saviour.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the body of Jeſus Chriſt celebrating the Sacrament was weak, paſſable and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>l, but the body which the Apoſtles received of him was impaſſible, and could ſuffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Let our adverſaries prove, if any ought to receive their opinion which giveth unto Jeſus Chriſt at the ſame time two bodies of contrary natures, or at leaſt one body contrary to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, when <hi>Victor</hi> the 3 Pope of that name was poyſoned in the Challice, and <hi>Henery</hi> the 7. in the Hoſt we demand what that was which was poyſoned, for to ſay the body of Jeſus Chriſt was poyſoned, is to prophane his body, what was it then with which they killed a Pope and a good Emporour? let them anſwer <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, but ſeeing we and you both agree that Jeſus Chriſt at the inſtitution of this Sacrament, he did eat and drink with his diſciples. We demanded, did Jeſus Chiſt eat his own body, and what profit that would be either to him or us, but if there be a corporall bodily ſubſtantiall preſence of Chriſts body and bloud in the Sacrament, by a change or converſion, of the bread and wine into the ſame body and bloud after the words of Conſecration, as you ſay there is, then he muſt needs eat his own body and drink his own bloud, which we put you to prove, if you ſay the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119379:13"/>of the body is within the body, its all one as if you ſhould ſay the ſheath is within the ſword <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, if Chriſts body be eaten corporally in the Sacrament, and that all that eate his fleſh and drink his bloud, have eternall life, as <hi>John</hi> 6.54. which you apply to the Sacrament; then ſhould wicked men, as well as the faithfull have eternall life: for they eat that which you ſay is the fleſh and bloud of Chriſt as well as the faithfull, if there be a corporal preſence in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Chriſt ſaid his body was the bread, his bloud it was the wine, they eat, they drank, yet he their ſhewed their feeding was divine.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, we demand how you prove it lawfull to pray in a language not underſtood of him that prayeth, ſeeing the Apoſtle in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.19. ſaith, I had rather ſpeak five words with my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that by my voyce I might teach others, than ten thouſand words in an unknown tonge, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.15. If I pray in an unknown tongue, my ſpirit prayeth, but my underſtanding is unfruitfull, therefore I will pray with the ſpirit and will pray with underſtanding alſo <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, we demand how you prove that we ought to adore the Croſſe with the ſame odora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that God is worſhipped withall, as <hi>Thomas</hi> and many other Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth, and if when the Preiſts ſaith to the Croſs, All hale triumphal wood, that wood underſtands what the Preiſt ſaith, ſeeing he ſpeaks to the wood, and where God hath commanded us to honour him thus.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, we demand how you prove it lawfull to have the Image of God, or of the Trinity in Churches repreſented in ſtone, or in pictures, ſeeing God hath forbidden it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>Take ye therefore good heed unto yourſelves (for ye ſaw no manner of ſimilitude on the day that the Lord spake unto you in Horch, out of the midſt of the fire.) Leſt you corupt your ſelves; and make you a graven image, the likeneſſe or ſimil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tude of any figure, the likeneſſe of male or female, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Twelfly, ſeeing the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holdeth that Infants which dye ſhortly after Baptiſme go ſtraight way into paradiſe. We demand whence it commeth that the Preiſts takes money, to pray and ſay Maſſes for them, and what profit redoundeth thereof unto their children.</p>
               <p>Thirtenthly, where is it that God hath Commanded that we ſhould offer Ieſus Chriſt as a Propitiatory ſacrifice for the quick and dead, ſeeing that you ſay the Prieſts calling is that they are eſtabliſhed to ſacrifice Jeſus Chriſt, Wee demand where, in what Scripture God hath eſtabliſhed them ſacrificers, ſeeing that Jeſus Chriſt doth not give that quality to his diſciples, and the new Teſtament doth not in any place call the paſtors of the Church Sacrificers.</p>
               <p n="14">14ly. We demand if, in the holy Scriptures there be any command not to eat fleſh on Friday, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing that Friday was the day in which Jeſus Chriſt did eate the paſcall lamb, and that the Apoſtle in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 3. ſayes they are ſeducers; and calls it the doctrine of the devil to forbid marriages, and command Abſtinence from meates which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving</p>
               <p n="15">15ly. When there were many Popes at once, and the ſtrongeſt Pope, carryed it, how will you prove that the ſtrongeſt, was the lawfull Pope, for if you prove not that the ſucceſſion hath often been interrupted, and they that followed are ſucceſſors of uſurping Popes, being choſen by <hi>Cardinalls,</hi> created by the preceding Pope, who not being the lawfull Pope had no Juſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to create <hi>Card<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nalls,</hi> nor thoſe <hi>Cardinalls,</hi> to choſe a Pope.</p>
               <p n="16">16ly. How do you prove that the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was rapt up in body into heaven, and there crowned Queen of heaven, for ſeeing ſhe is ſo repreſented in your Churches, and the people taught ſo, we demand how you prove it to be ſo.</p>
               <p n="17">17ly. We ſay that the Munks and Friars as they ſtand at this day, are thoſe the Apoſtle foretold of, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18 that do in voluntary humility worſhip angels and pray to them, not holding the head which is Chriſt, and therefore not holding the head there is no ſalvation to be had in any other: they alſo teach the people in ſome things, touch not, taſt not, handle nor, which all are to periſh, though they have a ſhew in will-worſhip and humility and neglecting of the body to the ſatisfying of the fleſh.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By <hi>George Preſſick.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
